Today we all have assembled here
Zebraliśmy się tutaj dzisiaj żeby
to pay our respect to Shri Ganesha.
oddać cześć Shri Ganeshy.
Ganapatipule has a special significance
Ganapatipule ma specjalne znaczenie -
because He is Mahaganesha.
- ponieważ On (Ganapati) jest Mahaganeshą.
The Ganesha at Mooladhara
Ganesha w Mooladharze
becomes Mahaganesha
staje się Mahaganeshą w Viracie,
in the Virata, that is the brain.
to znaczy w mózgu.
That means it is the seat of Shri Ganesha.
Oznacza to, że jest to miejsce Shri Ganeshy.
That means Shri Ganesha governs
To znaczy z tego miejsca Shri Ganesha
from that seat the principle of innocence.
zarządza zasadą niewinności.
As you know very well it is placed at the back
Jak dobrze wiecie to miejsce znajduje się z tyłu głowy
in the region of optic thalamus,
w regionie połączonym ze wzgórzem wzrokowym,
optic lobe as they call it,
w miejscu zwanym płatem wzrokowym;
and it is the giver of innocence to the eyes.
i ono daje niewinność oczom.
When He incarnated as Christ
Kiedy inkarnował On jako Chrystus -
which is in here in the front, at Agnya
- a znajduje się On tutaj z przodu, w Agnyi -
He said very clearly that
- powiedział to bardzo wyraźnie,
"Thou shalt not have adulterous eyes."
że "Nie będziesz miał pożądliwych oczu".
It's a very subtle saying,
To jest bardzo subtelne stwierdzenie,
which people don't understand
którego ludzie nie rozumieją,
what is the meaning of the word "adultery."
nie rozumieją znaczenia słowa "pożądliwe".
"Adultery" means "impurity" in a general word.
"Pożądliwość" generalnie oznacza "nieczystość".
Any impurity in the eye "thou shalt not have"
Żadnej nieczystości w oczach "nie będziesz miał" -
it's very difficult.
- to bardzo trudne.
Instead of saying that you get your realization
Zamiast powiedzieć, że lepiej dostać realizację
and clear your back Agnya,
i oczyścić tylną Agnyię,
He has said it in a very short form,
powiedział to w wielkim skrócie,
"Thou shalt not have adulterous eyes."
że "Nie będziesz miał pożądliwych oczu".
And people thought, it's an impossible situation.
A ludzie myśleli, że nie da się tego osiągnąć.
Because He was not allowed to live long;
Nie pozwolili mu długo żyć,
actually His public life is limited
właściwie jego życie publiczne było ograniczone
to three-and-a-half years only.
tylko do trzech i pół roku.
So whatever He has said has a very great significance,
Więc wszystko co mówił ma wielkie znaczenie.
that your eyes should not be adulterous.
A mówił, że wasze oczy nie powinny być pożądliwe.
When there is innocence there is no adultery:
Gdzie jest niewinność, tam nie ma pożądliwości,
it means there's no impurity.
to znaczy nie ma nieczystości.
For example, with our eyes
Na przykład,
we see something and we want to possess it.
widzimy coś naszymi oczami i chcemy to posiąść.
We start thinking.
Zaczynamy myśleć.
The thought starts
Zaczyna się łańcuch myśli,
like a chain, one after another.
jedna myśl po drugiej.
And then we get into the web of horrible thoughts,
I wtedy wplątujemy się w sieć okropnych myśli
and then we become slaves of those thoughts.
i stajemy się ich niewolnikami.
Without even our knowledge,
Bez naszej wiedzy,
our eyes are turned to things
nasze oczy kierują się na rzeczy,
which are very gross
które są przyziemne
and take you downward.
i one was pogrążają.
As Shri Krishna has said that the Tree of Awareness
Jak powiedział Shri Krishna, Drzewo Świadomości
grows upside-down,
rośnie do góry nogami,
that the roots are in the brain
tak, że korzenie są w mózgu
and the branches grow downward.
a gałęzie rosną do dołu.
Those who have gone towards materialism
Ci, którzy kierowali się materializmem,
have grown downward.
wyrośli w dół.
Those who have gone towards Divine
Ci, którzy kierowali się w stronę Boskości,
have grown upwards, towards the roots.
wyrośli w górę, w stronę korzeni.
The main root, as they call the taproot,
Korzeń główny, nazywany korzeniem palowym,
the main root is innocence, is Shri Ganesha.
ten główny korzeń jest niewinnością, jest Shri Ganeshą.
And He becomes Mahaganesha in Ganapatipule.
I On staje się Mahaganeshą w Ganapatipule.
Here He's surrounded
Tutaj On jest otoczony
by the Father Principle, the Guru Principle
Zasadą Ojca, Zasadą Guru,
of the sea, the ocean - the Indian Ocean.
którą jest morze, którą jest ocean - Ocean Indyjski.
That is, here He becomes a Guru.
Tak więc tutaj On staje się Guru
When a Sahaja yogi
Kiedy sahaja yogin
establishes his Shri Ganesha Principle,
ustanawia swoją Zasadę Shri Ganeshy
he's still a child.
nadal pozostaje dzieckiem.
Of course his eyes start becoming purer and purer,
Oczywiście jego oczy stają się coraz czystsze,
and powerful and glistening.
pełne siły i błyszczące.
You must have seen when the kundalini gives you
Na pewno widzieliście, że kiedy Kundalini
the realization
daje wam realizację
then your eyes start gleaming,
wasze oczy zaczynają świecić
like a spark is there in the eyes,
tak jakby była w nich iskra,
you can make out a spark.
dostrzegacie tę iskrę.
With ego it gets covered,
Może ona zostać zakryta przez ego,
with ego it blinds.
bo ego zaślepia.
With superego it is covered with tears.
A Superego zakrywa ją łzami.
But when they are clear
Ale kiedy oczy są czyste,
you see the beauty of the eyes,
widzicie ich piękno,
Shri Ganesha shining through your glances.
w waszych spojrzeniach świeci Shri Ganesha.
The attention now starts flowing
Uwaga zaczyna teraz płynąć
through the window of Shri Ganesha's temple.
przez okno świątyni Shri Ganeshy.
But when you mature,
Ale kiedy dojrzewacie
you become Mahaganesha.
stajecie się Mahaganeshą.
Then Mahaganesha is established in you
Wtedy Mahaganesha jest w was
and you become a satguru,
i stajecie się Satguru,
you become a divine guru, you can teach others.
Boskim Guru; możecie uczyć innych.
Even a child could be that
Nawet dziecko może się nim stać -
even a grown-up person may be stupid.
- tak jak nawet i dorosły może być głupcem.
It has nothing to do with age, color, creed or caste.
To nie ma nic wspólnego z wiekiem, kolorem, wyznaniem czy kastą.
It is a state to which one can reach at any time.
To jest stan, który w każdej chwili można osiągnąć.
Like we can say here we had Gyaneshwara,
Na przykład możemy powiedzieć, że mieliśmy Gyaneshwarę,
who at a very young age
który w bardzo wczesnym wieku
composed the great Gyaneshwari.
skomponował Gyaneshwari.
As you have seen yesterday,
Jak widzieliście wczoraj,
at the age of twelve years Gorakhnath
Gorakhnath mając dwanaście lat
established his Mahaganesha.
ustanowił swojego Mahaganeshę.
But if you do not try to ascend,
Ale jeśli nie próbujecie wzrastać,
then you'll remain at the same stage
wtedy pozostaniecie na tym samym poziomie,
even when you grow old.
nawet będąc w podeszłym wieku.
So maturity is the indication.
A więc wskaźnikiem jest dojrzałość.
Here, as we see in Ganapatipule,
Jak widzimy tutaj w Ganapatipule
Shri Ganesha is in its complete, matured form
Shri Ganesha jest w swojej kompletnej, dojrzałej postaci;
so that we develop also our Mahaganesha
po to abyśmy również rozwinęli Mahaganeshę
within ourselves,
w nas samych
and our eyes become pure, powerful and divine.
i aby nasze oczy stały się czyste, pełne siły i boskości.
With proper working out,
Jeżeli odpowiednio będziemy nad tym pracować,
I am sure we can establish that state within ourselves.
jestem pewna, że możemy osiągnąć ten stan.
Today we came to Ganapatipule, it has a great significance,
To bardzo znaczące, że przybyliśmy dzisiaj do Ganapatipule,
among the Asthavinayaka (eight Swayambhus of Shri Ganesha),
pomiędzy Asthavinayaki - ośmioma Swayambhu Shri Ganeshy.
It is the place of Mahaganesha.
To jest miejsce Mahaganeshy.
Mahaganesha is Pithadhish (Governor of all pithas)
Mahaganesha jest Pithadhish (zarządcą wszystkich pithas)
and sitting on this pitha,
i siedząc na tym pitha,
he protects all the Ganesha Swayambhus.
ochrania wszystkie Swayambhu Ganeshy.
He has the knowledge of all the Omkaras,
On posiada wiedzę wszystkich Omkara,
as he has attained the Guru Tatwa (Guru Principle).
jako że osiągnął Guru Tatwę (Zasadę Guru).
If we see in the surroundings,
Jeżeli rozejrzymy się dookoła -
the ocean, so beautiful and clean
- tak piękny i czysty ocean,
is washing the feet of this Ganapati,
obmywa stopy tego Ganapati,
because the ocean represents the Guru Tatwa,
dlatego że ocean reprezentuje Guru Tatwę
and with that Guru Tatwa, he washes the feet of Shri Ganesha
i właśnie tym Guru Tatwa on obmywa stopy Shri Ganeshy.
that is how it should happen with all the Sahaja Yogis.
I tak właśnie powinno się dziać ze wszystkimi sahaja yoginami.
Ganesha Stuthi is done and then Shri Ganesha is established
Dokonuje się Ganesha Stuthi i wtedy ustanowiony jest Shri Ganesha,
and thereafter with the Mahalaxmi Tatwa
a potem za pomocą Mahalaxmi Tatwy
you have to become Mahaganeshas.
musicie stać się Mahaganeshami.
This state can be achieved by children small and big,
Ten stan może być osiągnięty przez małe i duże dzieci,
elderly people, ladies and everyone,
ludzi starszych, kobiety - wszystkich,
if they can attain the straight forward behaviour,
którzy potrafią osiągnąć ten prosty sposób zachowania,
which we call as   Saralya  in Marathi, or they say Abhodita
zwany w języku Marathi "Saraliya" albo "Abhodita"
or innocence, when it is once imbibed in us,
albo niewinność. Raz zaszczepiony w nas,
we can achieve the Guru Principle.
pozwoli nam osiągnąć Zasadę Guru Pad.
Whichever Guru, who does not have this straight forward nature
Każdy Guru, który nie posiada tej prostej i niewinnej natury,
and innocence, he can never be a Guru,
nigdy nie będzie prawdziwym Guru,
he is a Aguru (false Guru).
jest Aguru (fałszywym Guru).
The person, whose attention is always on the Divine Power,
Tylko osoba, której uwaga jest cały czas skoncentrowana na Boskiej Mocy,
only he can become a real Guru.
może stać się prawdziwym Guru.
The attention of normal human beings is perverted,
Uwaga normalnych istot ludzkich jest wypaczona, nie jest czysta.
it is not clean. For this Christ has said,
To dlatego Chrystus powiedział,
there should be no adultery in your eyes,
że nie powinno być pożądliwości w waszych oczach.
means that if we put our attention on something,
Oznacza to, że jeśli nasza uwaga spocznie na czymś,
we start thinking a lot and strange thoughts come to our mind,
zaczynamy dużo myśleć i dziwne myśli przychodzą nam do głowy,
as to how I can acquire this thing
na przykład jak zdobyć tę rzecz,
and why I did not get this thing,
dlaczego tego nie mam
and other thoughts as to why and why not.
i inne myśli, dlaczego tak a nie inaczej.
If we see something and start thinking, then
Jeśli widzimy coś i zaczynamy myśleć,
you have not yet crossed the Agnya Chakra.
wtedy oznacza to, że nie przekroczyliśmy jeszcze Agnya Czakry.
Whatever object you see, you should become thoughtless,
Obojętnie co widzicie, powinniście móc wejść w stan świadomości bez myśli,
especially in the heavenly abode of wealth and prosperity
a szczególnie, jeśli widzi się Bogów i Boginie
there are numerous Gods and Goddesses
rezydujących w siedzibie bogactwa i dostatku -
at least by seeing them, one should become thoughtless.
- od samego patrzenia na nich powinniśmy stać się wolni od myśli.
Once we attain the state of thoughtless awareness,
Kiedy osiągniemy stan świadomości bez myśli,
no perversion will remain in our attention any more.
w naszej uwadze nie będzie już więcej żadnej perwersji.
The thoughts perverting the mind will not come anymore,
Myśli, które deprawują umysł nie będą już więcej przychodzić
so how will perversion influence you.
a więc perwersja nie będzie już miała na was żadnego wpływu.
That means like Christ said,
To właśnie oznacza, tak jak powiedział Chrystus,
thou shall not have adulterous eyes.
że nie będziesz miał pożądliwych oczu,
They should be so pure, like the rays of the sun,
twoje oczy będą tak klarowne jak promienie słońca,
when they fall on trees, they do no absorb the dirt,
kiedy padają na drzewa. One nie absorbują brudu,
they nourish and nurture them, not only that
ale pielęgnują i karmią,
but they also give them strength.
a ponadto dają siłę.
In a similar way,
W taki sam sposób
the Sahaja Yogis should have such radiance in their eyes, that
sahaja yogini powinni mieć promienność w oczach,
they can create a very pure atmosphere in the whole world.
żeby móc wykreować prawdziwie czystą atmosferę na całym świecie.
Purity in the atmosphere is what we need today, everywhere,
Czystość w atmosferze jest tym, czego dzisiaj najbardziej potrzebujemy
so that peace, joy and divine power can prevail in this world.
wszędzie żeby pokój, radość i Boska Moc zwyciężyła na tym świecie.
Only singing the praise of Shri Ganesha may not be sufficient,
Samo wychwalanie Shri Ganeshy śpiewem możne nie wystarczyć,
Shri Ganesha needs to be awakened within us
Shri Ganesha musi być w nas obudzony
and he should evolve to the state of Mahaganesha.
i powinien rozwinąć się do stanu Mahaganeshy.
Only after attaining the state of Mahaganesha,
Tylko po osiągnięciu stanu Mahaganeshy
can our country benefit and also through our country,
nasz kraj możne odnieść korzyść i poprzez nasz kraj
other countries can benefit from this state.
również i inne kraje skorzystają.
We are going to lead the others,
Będziemy prowadzić innych.
but if we do not take up this responsibility,
Ale jeśli nie przejmiemy tej odpowiedzialności,
then I cannot say, what will happen of this whole world.
wtedy nie wiem, co się stanie z tym całym światem.
I have a request to you all,
Mam do was wszystkich prośbę,
to remove all the adultery in your eyes.
abyście usunęli całą pożądliwość z waszych oczu.
For this we have the mantra of Nirvichara in Sahaja Yoga.
Po to mamy w Sahaja Yodze mantrę Nirvichara.
Do not allow the thoughts to dominate you,
Nie pozwólcie, żeby myśli was zdominowały,
if thoughts come, then say
jeśli myśli przyjdą, powiedzcie:
Yen Neti Neti Vachane  (it doesn't exist)
"Yen Neti Neti Vachane" (nie ma tego, nie ma...)
or say   Kshama Keli, Kshama Keli   (I forgive, I forgive),
albo powiedzcie: "Kshama Keli, Kshama Keli " (wybaczam, wybaczam),
so that this thought is destroyed
po to żeby ta myśl została zniszczona
and once thoughtlessness is attained,
i kiedy osiągnie się stan bez myśli,
then the perversion of the mind stops.
wtedy perwersja umysłu zatrzymuje się.
Everybody should make an attempt,
Każdy powinien podjąć wysiłek,
that your eyes are not adulterous.
żeby jego oczy nie były pożądliwe.
"If there is perversion in the mind because of my eyes,
"Jeśli jest perwersja w umyśle z powodu moich oczu,
then I do not want to have such eyes ", said Saint Tukaram,
to nie chcę mieć takich oczu" powiedział Święty Tukaram,
"then, it is better to be blind ".
"wtedy lepiej być ślepym".
In one way, it is better being blind,
Pod pewnym względem lepiej być ślepcem
than have perversion in the mind.
niż mieć zboczony umysł.
Rather have inner eyes to see Divinity.
Lepiej mieć wewnętrzne oczy, aby widzieć Boskość.
When these two principles come together properly,
Kiedy te dwie zasady zejdą się odpowiednio,
then one can say that
wtedy można powiedzieć,
the Sahaja Yogi has attained the Guru Principle.
że sahaja yogin osiągnął Zasadę Guru.
I bless you all, that here at Ganapatipule,
Błogosławię was wszystkich, żebyście tutaj w Ganapatipule,
the place of Mahaganesha, with his special grace,
miejscu Mahaganeshy, poprzez Jego łaskę
you all can attain your Guru Principle as soon as possible.
osiągnęli Zasadę Guru, tak szybko jak to tylko możliwe.
First they will take the twenty-four names of Shri Vishnu,
Najpierw powiedzą dwadzieścia cztery imiona Shri Vishnu,
so that this Sushumna Nadi will open out.
żeby Sushumna Nadi się otworzył.
Then they will say the Shri Sukta,
Potem powiedzą Shri Sukta,
is the one to awaken the energy within you.
to ten, który budzi w was energię.
Then they will say the 108 name of Mother Gauri.
A potem powiedzą 108 imion Matki Gauri.
After that pujan, when this puja is over,
A po tej pujy, kiedy puja się skończy,
then we will be doing a
wtedy będziemy robić... [Hindi].
Eleven kundas we have got,
Mamy jedenaście kundas
and we'll be doing the havana on eleven kundas.
i będziemy robić havan na jedenastu kundas.
Because the Mahaganesha is the ruler,
Dlatego, że Mahaganesha jest władcą
is the ruler of Ekadesha Rudra.
tych jedenastu Ekadesha Rudra.
So that has to be done with great devotion
To musi być spełnione z wielkim oddaniem
and dedication.
i poświęceniem.
I would suggest that first is finished this puja,
Więc sugeruję, aby najpierw skończyć tę puję,
you can have your food,
potem możecie coś zjeść,
and afterwards we'll sit down for the havan.
po czym usiądziemy do havanu.